Inventory of the Samuel H. Yonge Papers 1890-1935
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Samuel H. Yonge Papers 1890-1935
Special Collections Research Center
01/Mss. 65 Y8
557.00
Papers, 1890-1935, of Samuel Humphreys Yonge. Yonge was an army engineer who worked on flood control projects and navigational improvements. Yonge was interested in excavations at Jamestown and Williamsburg, Va. and in archaeological projects throughout Virginia. Included is correspondence; early twentieth century photographs of ruins and excavations at Jamestown; notebooks of land patent abstracts and other notes concerning Jamestown; and printed material. The collection also includes an account of Yonge's impressions of Robert E. Lee, president of Washington College (now Washington and Lee University) when Yonge was a student there and other autobiographical notes.
Yonge, Samuel Humphreys, b. 1850 arrangement
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Special Collections Research Center from Miss Arlene Ancher of Richmond, VA on 04/11/1941.
Biographical Note
Yonge was an army engineer who worked on flood control projects and navigational improvements. Yonge was interested in excavations at Jamestown and Williamsburg, Va. and in archaeological projects throughout Virginia. He was also the author of The Site of Old;James Towne 1607-1698. A brief Historical and Topographical Sketch of the First American Metropolis which has since been published in numerous editions. Further information about this individual or organization may be available in the Special Collections Research Center Wiki
Scope and Contents
Papers, 1890-1935, of Samuel Humphreys Yonge. Yonge was an army engineer who worked on flood control projects and navigational improvements. Yonge was interested in excavations at Jamestown and Williamsburg, Va. and in archaeological projects throughout Virginia. Included is correspondence; early twentieth century photographs of ruins and excavations at Jamestown; notebooks of land patent abstracts and other notes concerning Jamestown; and printed material. The collection also includes an account of Yonge's impressions of Robert E. Lee, president of Washington College (now Washington and Lee University) when Yonge was a student there and other autobiographical notes.
Additional Information
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
Genre/Form of Material:
Correspondence; Notebooks; Photographs
Personal Name:
Lee, Robert Edward (1807-1870)
Topical Term:
Archaeology--Methodology; Jamestown (Va.)--History--17th century; Virginia--History--Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Washington and Lee University--History; Williamsburg (Va.)--Colonial Period--History.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- (1)
    Series 1: Photographs, manuscripts and autobiographical notes
  - Photographs, manuscripts and autobiographical notes (1)
    - Photographs of ruins at Jamestown. (1)
      Early twentieth century photographs of ruins and excavations at Jamestown.
    - Picture of Wakefield., undated (1, 2)
      Picture of Wakefield; Washington’s Birthplace.
    - Yonge's impressions of Robert E. Lee, Undated (1, 3)
      Unpublished manuscript of Yonge's student impressions of Robert E. Lee as president of Washington and Lee University. Includes members. Correspondences between Yonge and others about his manuscripts.
    - Manuscripts, etc., Undated (1, 4)
      Manuscript of Phi Beta Kappa address at Jamestown, Nov 1926. Manuscript of Yonge's address before the American Society of Mechanical Engineers. Letter from G. Tyler, enclosing map of early street layout of Jamestown. Remarks on English settlements of Virginia. Memorial for remarks at Jamestown in the Memorial Church. Journal of Assembly of V.A.. Library of Congress Copyright. Souvenir of the Church at Old Jamestown.
    - Autobiographical notes, Photographic copy of James River and Map of James City., 1856; 1607-1698 (1, 5)
      Yonge's autobiographical notes. Photographic copy of 1856 hydrographic survey of the James River in vicinity of Jamestown. Yonge's map of James City, V.A., 1607-1698.
- (2)
    Series 2: Notebooks and Printed Material on James River, Jamestown and surrounding area.
  - Notebooks and Printed Material on James River, Jamestown and surrounding area. (2)
    Two manuscript notebooks containing memos from land patent records of James City Island. Printed works: Government Report Upon the Improvement of Rivers and Harbors in the Norfolk, Virginia District, 1914, 1918, 1919, 1920, 1921, 1922, 1923, 1925, 1926. Jamestown and James River souvenir booklets, A Brief History of and Guide Book to Jamestown, Williamsburg, and Yorktown. Rutherford Goodwin, 1930. Official Guide Book Jamestown Centennial Exposition, 1907. Notes on a Journey on the James, 1907. Report of Investigation with Reference to Improving the James River Technical Advisory Corp., 1924. James River from the Head of the Tidewater to Hampton Roads as a National Waterway, 1886.
- (3)
    Series 3: Newspaper Clippings, Notes and manuscript on Jamestown and Bridge
  - Newspaper Clippings, Notes and manuscript on Jamestown and Bridge (3)
    A volume of newspaper clippings, 1898-1935, of persons, homes, places, and events of historic interest. Eighty-four page manuscript volume of notes on Jamestown and on bridge construction there. One-hundred ninety-six page manuscript volume of notes on Jamestown. Letters to the Virginia Pilot Concerns; “Location of Grave of Pocahontas”.
- (4)
    Series 4: Correspondence
  - Correspondence (4)
    - Personal notes to Yonge, 1921; 1928 (4, 1)
      Personal and social notes to Yonge, including invitation to installation of Dr. J. A. C. Chandler as president of William and Mary in 1921; opening of James River Bridge, 1928.
    - Letters from Onward Bates (4, 2)
      Letters from Onward Bates, reviewing a life-time friendship of over sixty years.
    - Letters from Philip A. Bruce. (4, 3)
      Letters from Philip A. Bruce.
    - Letter from John Stewart Bryan (4)
      Letter from John Stewart Bryan, attaching blueprints and recommendations for remodeling and making addition to Virginia Historical Society building, 1932.
    - Correspondence with APVA (4, 5)
    - Correspondence with D.A.R. Goodwin, 1928 (4, 6)
    - Correspondence with Bradford Kilby, 1923 (4, 7)
      Correspondence with Bradford Kilby 1923. Society for Preservation of Va. Antiquities in Suffolk. Includes pictures.
    - Correspondence with Gaston Lichtenstein. (4, 8)
    - Correspondence with Mrs. John B. Lightfoot (4, 9)
    - Correspondence with Morgan P. Robinson. (4, 10)
    - Correspondence with Mrs. Virginia Taylor (4, 11)
    - Correspondence with M. Wilmer (4, 12)
    - Correspondence with Daniel Grihnan (4, 13)
    - Correspondence with William G. Standard (4, 14)
    - Correspondence with Benjamin S. Hayne (4, 15)
    - APVA Correspondence (4, 16)
    - Virginia Historical Society (4, 17)
- (5)
    Series 5: Correspondences and Letters
  - Correspondences and Letters (5)
    - Correspondence with Dr. W.A. R. Goodwin; Misc. letters, 1928 (5, 1)
      Correspondence with Dr. W.A. R. Goodwin, 1928. Misc. letters.
    - Misc. correspondence, 1933-1935 (5, 2)
    - Correspondences between APVA and architects of colonial Williamsburg, 1928-1930 (5, 3)
      Correspondence between APVA committee and architects of Colonial Williamsburg, 1928-1930. Handwritten letters.
    - Letters from J.A C. Chandler (5, 4)
      Letters from J.A C. Chandler discussing Phi Beta Kappa.
- (6)
    Series 6: Notes and Letters
  - Notes and Letters (6)
    - Speaking about Jamestown and The Book, 1904-1926 (6, 1)
      The Book 1904-1926. Articles 1903-1929. Speaking about Jamestown 1904-1926.
    - Handwritten notes on Jamestown together with a guide to Old Jamestown. (6, 2)
    - PBK. Engineering societies. Clubs., 1888-1930 (6, 3)
    - Tombs: Hollywood Cemetery Comp. John Tyler Monument (6, 4)
    - Handwritten notes on Capitol restoration, 1909-1932 (6, 5)
      Handwritten notes on Capitol restoration. Perry, Shaw and Hepburn Architects. (1909-1932). Correspondence about Capitol 1928-1931.
    - E. G. Swem. Capitol restoration., 1928 (6)